<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>biostatistics on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/biostatistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in biostatistics on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/biostatistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in COVID-19 modelling</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/02/04/covid-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/02/04/covid-webinar/</guid>
      <description>YoungStatS project of Young Statisticians Europe, FENStatS, proudly announces our first One World YoungStatS webinar. With four young scholars, we will discuss Recent Advances in the Modelling of COVID-19, presenting novel statistical models, interesting advancements and applications of mechanistic models, as well as their combinations.
When: Wednesday, February 10th, 16:00 (Central European Time).
Speakers:
 Cécile Tran Kiem (Institute Pasteur, Paris, France) Pierfrancesco Alaimo Di Loro and Marco Mingione (StatGroup-19, Italy) Kevin Kunzmann (University of Cambridge, United Kingdom)  Discussant:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making an Online Risk Calculator</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/11/11/online-risk-calc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/11/11/online-risk-calc/</guid>
      <description>We first started making risk calculators with the website, http://nomograms.org.There are several here, and they are patient friendly.Later, we launched rcalc.ccf.org, which has many more risk calculators, although the intended audience is the clinician. It is considerably more expensive and time-consuming to make these patient friendly. There were many obstacles to overcome in making these websites. Here is an example (Figure 1), from prostate cancer research where our calculator assists with an optional treatment by showing the 4-year risks of several outcomes for both options:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
