<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Econometrics on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/econometrics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Econometrics on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/econometrics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advancements in Applied Instrumental Variable Methods</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/07/recent-advancements-in-applied-instrumental-variable-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/07/recent-advancements-in-applied-instrumental-variable-methods/</guid>
      <description>Recent Advancements in Applied Instrumental Variable Methods&#xA;Instrumental variables (IV) is one of most important and widespread research designs in economics and statistics, as it can identify causal effects in the presence of unobserved confounding. Over the past 30 years the science of IV has advanced considerably, in part through the contributions of Nobel Laureates Joshua Angrist, Guido Imbens, and James Heckman. Recent years have brought significant advances in how IV is applied, in shift-share designs, with judge or examiner instruments, and in settings with rich or complex controls.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advances in Difference-in-Differences in Econometrics</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advances-in-difference-in-differences-in-econometrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advances-in-difference-in-differences-in-econometrics/</guid>
      <description>Advances in Difference-in-Differences in Econometrics&#xA;The eighth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place&#xD;on December 15th, 2021. The difference-in-differences design is a&#xD;quasi-experimental identification strategy for estimating causal effects&#xD;which has become the single most popular research design in the&#xD;quantitative social sciences, and as such, it merits careful study by&#xD;researchers everywhere. It is also a flourishing field of present&#xD;research in econometrics. Selected younger researchers active in the&#xD;area will present their recent contributions on this topic.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
