<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>stochastic-processes on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/stochastic-processes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in stochastic-processes on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/stochastic-processes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Regularization by Noise for Stochastic Differential and Stochastic Partial Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/06/03/regularization-by-noise-for-stochastic-differential-and-stochastic-partial-differential-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/06/03/regularization-by-noise-for-stochastic-differential-and-stochastic-partial-differential-equations/</guid>
      <description>Regularization by Noise for Stochastic Differential and Stochastic Partial Differential Equations
The regularizing effects of noisy perturbations of differential equations is a central subject of stochastic analysis. Recent breakthroughs initiated a new wave of interest, particularly concerning non-Markovian, infinite dimensional, and rough-stochastic / Young-stochastic hybrid systems.
On the webinar, selected younger scholars will present their recent works on the topic.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Wednesday, September 21st, 7:00 PT / 10:00 EST / 16:00 CET.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring dependence in the Wasserstein distance for Bayesian nonparametric models</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/17/measuring-dependence-in-the-wasserstein-distance-for-bayesian-nonparametric-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/17/measuring-dependence-in-the-wasserstein-distance-for-bayesian-nonparametric-models/</guid>
      <description>OverviewBayesian nonparametric (BNP) models are a prominent tool for performing flexible inference with a natural quantification of uncertainty. Traditionallly, flexible inference within a homogeneous sample is performed with exchangeable models of the type \(X_1,\dots, X_n|\tilde \mu \sim T(\tilde \mu)\), where \(\tilde \mu\) is a random measure and \(T\) is a suitable transformation. Notable examples for \(T\) include normalization for random probabilities (Regazzini et al., 2003), kernel mixtures for densities (Lo, 1984) and for hazards (Dykstra and Laud, 1981; James, 2005), exponential transformations for survival functions (Doksum, 1974) and cumulative transformations for cumulative hazards (Hjort, 1990).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inclusion Process and Sticky Brownian Motions</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/24/inclusion-process-and-sticky-brownian-motions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/24/inclusion-process-and-sticky-brownian-motions/</guid>
      <description>Inclusion Process and Sticky Brownian Motions
The ninth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place onFebruary 9th, 2022. Inclusion process (IP) is a stochastic lattice gaswhere particles perform random walks subjected to mutual attraction. Forthe inclusion process in the condensation regime one can extract thatthe scaling limit of two particles is a pair of sticky Brownian motionswhich lead to interesting recent research. In a system of stickyBrownian motions, particles behave as independent Brownian motions whenapart, but have a sticky interaction when they meet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frozen percolation on the binary tree is nonendogenous</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/11/25/frozen-percolation-on-the-binary-tree-is-nonendogenous/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/11/25/frozen-percolation-on-the-binary-tree-is-nonendogenous/</guid>
      <description>In frozen percolation on a graph, there is a barrier located on eachedge. Initially, the barriers are closed and they are assignedi.i.d. uniformly distributed activation times. At its activation time,a barrier opens, provided it is not frozen. At a fixed set \(\Xi\) offreezing times, all barriers that percolate are frozen. In particular,if \(\Xi\) is the whole unit interval, this means that clusters stopgrowing as soon as they reach infinite size.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
