<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>PLS for Big Data: A unified parallel algorithm for regularised group PLS</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/01/28/pls-for-big-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/01/28/pls-for-big-data/</guid>
      <description>We look at the problem of learning latent structure between two blocks of data through the partial least squares (PLS) approach. These methods include approaches for supervised and unsupervised statistical learning. We review these methods and present approaches to decrease the computation time and scale the method to big data
Given two blocks of data, the PLS approach seeks latent variables which are constructed as linear combinations of the original datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning for causal inference that works</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/01/26/machine-learning-for-causal-inference-that-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/01/26/machine-learning-for-causal-inference-that-works/</guid>
      <description>I’ve kindly been invited to share a few words about a recent paper my colleagues and I published in Bayesian Analysis: “Bayesian Regression Tree Models for Causal Inference: Regularization, Confounding, and Heterogeneous Effects”. In that paper, we motivate and describe a method that we call Bayesian causal forests (BCF), which is now implemented in an R package called bcf.
The goal of this post is to work through a simple toy example to illustrate the strengths of BCF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Mulitple Latent Block Model for mixed data</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/01/05/mlbm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/01/05/mlbm/</guid>
      <description>body { text-align: justify}  Abstract Co-clustering techniques, which group observations and features simultaneously, have proven to be efficient in summarising data sets. They exploit the dualism between rows and columns and the data set is summarized in blocks (the crossing of a row-cluster and a column-cluster). However, in the case of mixed data sets (with features of different kind), it is not easy to define a co-clustering method that takes this heterogeneity into account.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Causal discovery in the presence of discrete latent variables</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/15/icph/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/15/icph/</guid>
      <description>We address the problem of causal structure learning in the presence of hidden variables. Given a target variable and a vector of covariates, we are trying to infer the set of observable causal parents of the target variable. There are many good reasons for being interested in causal predictors.
Given a target variable $Y$, and a vector $X = (X^1, \dots, X^d)$ of $d$ covariates, we are trying to infer the set $S^* \subseteq \{1, \dots, d\}$ of observable causal parents of $Y$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Regression Control Chart: a New Framework for Profile Monitoring
</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/04/functional-regression-control-chart/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/04/functional-regression-control-chart/</guid>
      <description>Introduction New statistical process control (SPC) methods have to be developed in order to handle more and more complex data, which are available because of the advent of new data acquisition technologies. In particular, in many practical situations the quality characteristic of a process can be modelled as a function defined on a compact domain, data of such kind are the foundation of a rapidly expanding area of statistics referred to as functional data analysis (FDA).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online cash register data in the measurement of retail trade turnover</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/03/abel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/03/abel/</guid>
      <description>The Hungarian Central Statistical Office uses online cash register data for the measurement of retail trade and food services. The data source allows the statistical office to considerably cut administrative burden of data providers without quality loss in retail trade statistics. Online cash register data is widely used in tracking the latest developments in retail trade during the coronavirus pandemic as well.
Online cash registers (online pénztárgép &amp;ndash; OPG) were introduced in Hungary in 2013.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making an Online Risk Calculator</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/11/11/online-risk-calc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/11/11/online-risk-calc/</guid>
      <description>We first started making risk calculators with the website, http://nomograms.org. There are several here, and they are patient friendly. Later, we launched rcalc.ccf.org, which has many more risk calculators, although the intended audience is the clinician. It is considerably more expensive and time-consuming to make these patient friendly. There were many obstacles to overcome in making these websites. Here is an example (Figure 1), from prostate cancer research where our calculator assists with an optional treatment by showing the 4-year risks of several outcomes for both options:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble Forecasting of the Zika Space-Time Spread with Topological Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/22/soliman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/22/soliman/</guid>
      <description>As per the records of the World Health Organization, the first formally reported incidence of Zika virus occurred in Brazil in May 2015. The disease then rapidly spread to other countries in Americas and East Asia, affecting more than 1,000,000 people. Zika virus is primarily transmitted through bites of infected mosquitoes of the species Aedes (Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus). The abundance of mosquitoes and, as a result, the prevalence of Zika virus infections are common in areas which have high precipitation, high temperature, and high population density.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Tale of Two Parasites...one statistician&#39;s career journey</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/05/par_diggle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/05/par_diggle/</guid>
      <description>Vector-borne diseases have long presented major challenges to the health of rural communities in the wet tropical regions of the world, but especially in sub-Saharan Africa. In this paper, we describe the contribution that statistical modelling has made to the global elimination programme for one vector-borne disease, onchocerciasis.
Perhaps more than anything else I have written, this paper captures my career journey from stochastic process theory to tropical disease epidemiology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Approach to Treatment Selection to Benefit Patient Outcomes in Clinical Trials</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/04/mozgunov/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/04/mozgunov/</guid>
      <description>1Introduction: Selecting Best Treatment The question of selecting the &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; amongst different choices is a common problem in our lives. In clinical trials, our main field research, the question usually translates to &amp;ldquo;Out of a number of alternative treatments, which one treats the patients best?&amp;rdquo;.
A traditional approach to answer this question is to randomise equal numbers of patients to new treatments and the current method of treatment used in practice, called standard of care (SoC).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling COVID-19 pandemic using Bayesian analysis with application to Slovene data</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/01/modeling-covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/01/modeling-covid-19/</guid>
      <description>As the COVID-19 pandemic spread across the world at the beginning of 2020, statistically modeling its development became of big interest. The main focus of this work was to analyze the spread of the disease and its main characteristics for Slovenia using publicly available COVID-19 data. Our work takes a Bayesian semiparametric approach using which we estimate some of the main measures of interest for the pandemic (e.g. the reproduction number $R_{t}$) and give accurate forecasts of important indicators for the following days.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The scientific collaboration of researchers and organizations in Slovenia</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/01/cugmas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/10/01/cugmas/</guid>
      <description>As a scientific community, we must understand how scientific collaboration (SC) works on both the individual and organizational levels to be able to propose R&amp;amp;D policies that are efficient. Unfortunately, the interdependent nature of SC among different levels is often not well considered in empirical studies. To address this issue, we will present the scientometric approach that provides a simultaneous insight into SC patterns on both levels: among researchers (individual level) and organizations (organizational level).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One World YoungStatS</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/09/10/webinars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/09/10/webinars/</guid>
      <description>One World YoungStatS webinar
We are delighted to announce the creation of the One World YoungStatS Webinar series! Our goal in creating this seminar series is to provide a platform for our community to continue interacting and growing in spite of the current health crisis and ever since. The YoungStatS webinar series will accompany the YoungStatS blog and provide insight into best and most recent work done in all areas of statistics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to our blog!</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/09/01/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/09/01/welcome/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our blog! This website is set up to promote research in statistics in its broadest sense, encompassing all of its areas and applications, among other mathematical statistics and probability, official statistics, biostatistics and medical statistics, social statistics, economic statistics and econometrics, environmental statistics, statistics in natural sciences, data science and survey methods. The intended audiences are in particular young researchers and scholars in statistics, but also research community in statistics in general, practitioners in the field, advisory councils, institutions, academia, the private sector as well as journalists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About US</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>About
The YoungStatS Blog is set up to promote research in statistics in its broadest sense, encompassing all of its areas and applications, among other mathematical statistics and probability, official statistics, biostatistics and medical statistics, social statistics, economic statistics and econometrics, environmental statistics, statistics in natural sciences, data science and survey methods. The intended audiences are in particular young researchers and scholars in statistics, but also research community in statistics in general, practitioners in the field, advisory councils, institutions, academia, the private sector as well as journalists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online Seminars</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/seminars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/seminars/</guid>
      <description>One World YoungStatS webinar
We are delighted to announce the creation of the One World YoungStatS webinar Series! Our goal in creating this seminar series is to provide a platform for our community to continue interacting and growing in spite of the current health crisis. The Online Seminar Series will accompany the YoungStatS blog and provide insight into best and most recent work done in all areas of statistics
Seminars will be held on Zoom on Wednesday at 4:00 pm CET (10:00 am ET / 9:00 am CT / 7:00 am PT).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
