<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>YoungStatS</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Program Evaluation and Causal Inference for Histogram Data</title>
      <link>/post/2020/09/11/2020program-evaluation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/09/11/2020program-evaluation/</guid>
      <description>Program Evaluation and Causal Inference for Histogram Data
By Andrej Srakar, Valentina Prevolnik-Rupel and Tjaša Bartolj
Analysis of compositions, intervals, histograms, distributions and functions has become more and more common in contemporary statistics and econometrics. Despite several types of regressions existing for symbolic data, causal inference has not been studied so far adequately. We develop a statistical theory for using instrumental variables with symbolic distributional data, related to the prevailing usage of regressions in such situations, the so-called &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We&#39;re online</title>
      <link>/post/2020/09/10/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/09/10/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our blog! This website is set up to promote research in statistics in its broadest sense, encompassing all of its areas and applications, among other mathematical statistics and probability, official statistics, biostatistics and medical statistics, social statistics, economic statistics and econometrics, environmental statistics, statistics in natural sciences, data science and survey methods. The intended audiences are in particular young researchers and scholars in statistics, but also research community in statistics in general, practitioners in the field, advisory councils, institutions, academia, the private sector as well as journalists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About US</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>About
The YoungStatS Blog is set up to promote research in statistics in its broadest sense, encompassing all of its areas and applications, among other mathematical statistics and probability, official statistics, biostatistics and medical statistics, social statistics, economic statistics and econometrics, environmental statistics, statistics in natural sciences, data science and survey methods. The intended audiences are in particular young researchers and scholars in statistics, but also research community in statistics in general, practitioners in the field, advisory councils, institutions, academia, the private sector as well as journalists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online Seminars</title>
      <link>/seminars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/seminars/</guid>
      <description>YoungStatS Online Seminar
We are delighted to announce the creation of the YoungStatS Online Seminar Series (YSOS)! Our goal in creating this seminar series is to provide a platform for our community to continue interacting and growing in spite of the current health crisis. The Online Seminar Series will accompany the YoungStatS blog and provide insight into best and most recent work done in all areas of statistics
Seminars will be held on Zoom on Tuesday at 8:30 am PT (10:30 am CT / 11:30 am ET / 5:30 pm CET).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>