<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>probability on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/probability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in probability on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/probability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Log-modulated rough stochastic volatility models</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/14/log-modulated-rough-stochastic-volatility-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/14/log-modulated-rough-stochastic-volatility-models/</guid>
      <description>Rough VolatilityNew insights about the regularity of the instantaneous variance obtained from realized variance data (see Gatheral, Jaisson, and Rosenbaum (2018), Bennedsen, Lunde, and Pakkanen (2021, to appear), Fukasawa, Takabatake, and Westphal (2019)), have inspired the development of so-called stochastic volatility models in the financial literature.In simple terms, such a model can be described by the following SDE\[\begin{equation}\label{eq:stoch-vol}dS_t = S_t \sqrt{v_t}dB_t,\end{equation}\]where the logarithm of the instantaneous variance process \(v\) behaves similarly to a fractional Brownian motion (fBm) with Hurst index \(0 &amp;lt; H &amp;lt; 1/2\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Homogeneous Poisson Process Intensity Modeling and Estimation using Measure Transport</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/19/non-homogeneous-poisson-process-intensity-modeling-and-estimation-using-measure-transport/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/19/non-homogeneous-poisson-process-intensity-modeling-and-estimation-using-measure-transport/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionA NHPP defined on \({\cal S} \subset \mathbb{R}^{d}\) can be fullycharacterized through its intensity function \(\lambda: {\cal S} \rightarrow [0, \infty)\).We present a general model for the intensity function of a non-homogeneous Poissonprocess using measure transport. The model finds its roots in transportation ofprobability measure (Marzouk et al. 2016), an approach that has gainedpopularity recently for its ability to model arbitrary probabilitydensity functions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regularization by Noise for Stochastic Differential and Stochastic Partial Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/06/03/regularization-by-noise-for-stochastic-differential-and-stochastic-partial-differential-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/06/03/regularization-by-noise-for-stochastic-differential-and-stochastic-partial-differential-equations/</guid>
      <description>Regularization by Noise for Stochastic Differential and Stochastic Partial Differential Equations
The regularizing effects of noisy perturbations of differential equations is a central subject of stochastic analysis. Recent breakthroughs initiated a new wave of interest, particularly concerning non-Markovian, infinite dimensional, and rough-stochastic / Young-stochastic hybrid systems.
On the webinar, selected younger scholars will present their recent works on the topic.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Wednesday, September 21st, 7:00 PT / 10:00 EST / 16:00 CET.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inclusion Process and Sticky Brownian Motions</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/24/inclusion-process-and-sticky-brownian-motions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/24/inclusion-process-and-sticky-brownian-motions/</guid>
      <description>Inclusion Process and Sticky Brownian Motions
The ninth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place onFebruary 9th, 2022. Inclusion process (IP) is a stochastic lattice gaswhere particles perform random walks subjected to mutual attraction. Forthe inclusion process in the condensation regime one can extract thatthe scaling limit of two particles is a pair of sticky Brownian motionswhich lead to interesting recent research. In a system of stickyBrownian motions, particles behave as independent Brownian motions whenapart, but have a sticky interaction when they meet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frozen percolation on the binary tree is nonendogenous</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/11/25/frozen-percolation-on-the-binary-tree-is-nonendogenous/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/11/25/frozen-percolation-on-the-binary-tree-is-nonendogenous/</guid>
      <description>In frozen percolation on a graph, there is a barrier located on eachedge. Initially, the barriers are closed and they are assignedi.i.d. uniformly distributed activation times. At its activation time,a barrier opens, provided it is not frozen. At a fixed set \(\Xi\) offreezing times, all barriers that percolate are frozen. In particular,if \(\Xi\) is the whole unit interval, this means that clusters stopgrowing as soon as they reach infinite size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Concentration Inequalities in Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>The fifth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place on September 15th, 2021. Selected young European researchers active in the areas of probability and machine learning will present their recent contributions. The webinar is joint cooperation between the Young Researchers Committee of the Bernoulli Society and the YoungStatS project.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Wednesday, September 15th, 17:00 CESTOnline, via Zoom. The registration form is available here.Speakers:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
