<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine-Learning on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Machine-Learning on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Extrapolation to unseen domains: from theory to applications</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2024/04/05/extrapolation-generalization-to-novel-domains-in-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2024/04/05/extrapolation-generalization-to-novel-domains-in-data-science/</guid>
      <description>Extrapolation to unseen domains: from theory to applications&#xA;Monday, April 22nd, 2024, 8:00 PT / 11:00 ET / 17:00 CET&#xA;3rd joint webinar of the IMS New Researchers Group, Young Data Science Researcher Seminar Zürich and the YoungStatS Project.&#xA;When &amp;amp; Where:&#xA;Monday, April 22nd, 2024, 8:00 PT / 11:00 ET / 17:00 CET&#xD;Online, via Zoom. The registration form is available&#xD;here.&#xD;Speakers:&#xA;Max Simchowitz, Robot Locomotion Group, MIT: “Statistical Learning under Heterogeneous Distribution Shift”&#xD;Abstract: What makes a trained predictor, e.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear-cost unbiased estimator for large crossed random effect models via couplings</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/09/27/linear-cost-unbiased-estimator-for-large-crossed-random-effect-models-via-couplings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/09/27/linear-cost-unbiased-estimator-for-large-crossed-random-effect-models-via-couplings/</guid>
      <description>In the following we show how it is possible to obtain parallelizable, unbiased and computationally cheap estimates of Crossed random effects models with a linear cost in the number of datapoints (and paramaters) exploiting couplings.&#xA;Crossed random effects models (CREM)&#xD;CREM model a continuous response variables \(Y\) as depending on the sum of unknown effects of \(K\) categorical predictors. Think of the \(Y_n\) as the ratings given to university courses, along with some factors potentially impacting such a score, e.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Fairness</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/09/19/algorithmic-fairness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/09/19/algorithmic-fairness/</guid>
      <description>Algorithmic Fairness&#xA;Tuesday, October 3rd, 2023, 7:30 PT / 10:30 ET / 16:30 CET&#xA;2nd joint webinar of the IMS New Researchers Group, Young Data Science Researcher Seminar Zürich and the YoungStatS Project.&#xA;When &amp;amp; Where:&#xA;Tuesday, October 3rd, 2023, 7:30 PT / 10:30 ET / 16:30 CET&#xD;Online, via Zoom. The registration form is available&#xD;here.&#xD;Speakers:&#xA;Linjun Zhang, Rutgers University: “Fair conformal prediction”&#xD;Abstract: Multi-calibration is a powerful and evolving concept originating in the field of algorithmic fairness.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distribution generalization and causal inference</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/02/28/distribution-generalization-in-causal-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/02/28/distribution-generalization-in-causal-inference/</guid>
      <description>Distribution generalization and causal inference&#xA;Monday, March 20th, 2023, 7:00 PT / 10:00 ET / 15:00 CET&#xA;1st joint webinar of the IMS New Researchers Group, Young Data Science Researcher Seminar Zürich and the YoungStatS Project.&#xA;When &amp;amp; Where:&#xA;Monday, March 20th, 2023, 7:00 PT / 10:00 ET / 15:00 CET&#xD;Online, via Zoom. The registration form is available&#xD;here.&#xD;Speakers:&#xA;Zijian Guo, Rutgers University: “Statistical Inference for Maximin Effects: Identifying Stable Associations across Multiple Studies”&#xD;Abstract: Integrative analysis of data from multiple sources is critical to making generalizable discoveries.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inference on Adaptively Collected Data</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/11/inference-on-adaptively-collected-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/11/inference-on-adaptively-collected-data/</guid>
      <description>Abstract&#xD;It is increasingly common for data to be collected adaptively, where&#xD;experimental costs are reduced progressively by assigning promising&#xD;treatments more frequently. However, adaptivity also poses great&#xD;challenges on post-experiment inference, since observations are&#xD;dependent, and standard estimates can be skewed and heavy-tailed. We&#xD;propose a treatment-effect estimator that is consistent and&#xD;asymptotically normal, allowing for constructing frequentist confidence&#xD;intervals and testing hypotheses.&#xA;Introduction&#xD;Adaptive data collection can optimize sample efficiency during the&#xD;course of the experiment for particular objectives, such as identifying&#xD;the best treatment (D.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Homogeneous Poisson Process Intensity Modeling and Estimation using Measure Transport</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/19/non-homogeneous-poisson-process-intensity-modeling-and-estimation-using-measure-transport/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/19/non-homogeneous-poisson-process-intensity-modeling-and-estimation-using-measure-transport/</guid>
      <description>Introduction&#xD;A NHPP defined on \({\cal S} \subset \mathbb{R}^{d}\) can be fully&#xD;characterized through its intensity function \(\lambda: {\cal S} \rightarrow [0, \infty)\).&#xD;We present a general model for the intensity function of a non-homogeneous Poisson&#xD;process using measure transport. The model finds its roots in transportation of&#xD;probability measure (Marzouk et al. 2016), an approach that has gained&#xD;popularity recently for its ability to model arbitrary probability&#xD;density functions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimax Estimation and Identity Testing of Markov Chains</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/18/minimax-estimation-and-identity-testing-of-markov-chains/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/18/minimax-estimation-and-identity-testing-of-markov-chains/</guid>
      <description>We briefly review the two classical problems of distribution estimation&#xD;and identity testing (in the context of property testing), then propose&#xD;to extend them to a Markovian setting. We will see that the sample&#xD;complexity depends not only on the number of states, but also on the&#xD;stationary and mixing properties of the chains.&#xA;The distribution setting&#xD;Estimation/Learning. A fundamental problem in statistics is to&#xD;estimate a probability distribution from independent samples.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory and Methods for Inference in Multi-armed Bandit Problems</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/04/19/theory-and-methods-for-inference-in-multi-armed-bandit-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/04/19/theory-and-methods-for-inference-in-multi-armed-bandit-problems/</guid>
      <description>Theory and Methods for Inference in Multi-armed Bandit Problems&#xA;Multi-armed bandit (MAB) algorithms have been argued for decades as useful to conduct adaptively-randomized experiments. By skewing the allocation of the arms towards the more efficient or informative ones, they have the potential to enhance participants’ welfare, while resulting in a more flexible, efficient, and ethical alternative compared to traditional fixed studies. However, such allocation strategies complicate the problem of statistical inference.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneous Treatment Effects with Instrumental Variables: A Causal Machine Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/06/heterogeneous-treatment-effects-with-instrumental-variables-a-causal-machine-learning-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/06/heterogeneous-treatment-effects-with-instrumental-variables-a-causal-machine-learning-approach/</guid>
      <description>Problem Setting&#xD;In our forthcoming paper on Annals of Applied Statistics, we propose a new method – which we call Bayesian Causal Forest with Instrumental Variable (BCF-IV) – to interpretably discover the subgroups with the largest or smallest causal effects in an instrumental variable setting.&#xA;These are many situations, ranging in complexity and importance, where one would like to estimate the causal effect of a defined intervention on a specific outcome.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concentration Inequalities in Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>The fifth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place on September 15th, 2021. Selected young European researchers active in the areas of probability and machine learning will present their recent contributions. The webinar is joint cooperation between the Young Researchers Committee of the Bernoulli Society and the YoungStatS project.&#xA;When &amp;amp; Where:&#xA;Wednesday, September 15th, 17:00 CEST&#xD;Online, via Zoom. The registration form is available here.&#xD;Speakers:</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
