<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Graphical-Models on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/graphical-models/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Graphical-Models on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/graphical-models/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Illustration of Graphical Gaussian Process models to analyze highly multivariate spatial data</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/07/07/illustration-of-graphical-gaussian-process-models-to-analyze-highly-multivariate-spatial-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/07/07/illustration-of-graphical-gaussian-process-models-to-analyze-highly-multivariate-spatial-data/</guid>
      <description>Introduction&#xD;Abundant multivariate spatial data from the natural and environmental sciences demands research on the joint distribution of multiple spatially dependent variables (Wackernagel (2013), Cressie and Wikle (2011), Banerjee and Gelfand (2014)). Here, our goal is to estimate associations over spatial locations for each variable and those among the variables.&#xA;In this document, we will present an example of a simulated multivariate spatial data and how we can use Graphical Gaussian processes (GGP) (Dey and Banerjee (2021)) to model the data.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphical modeling of stochastic processes driven by correlated noise</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/27/graphical-modeling-of-stochastic-processes-driven-by-correlated-noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/27/graphical-modeling-of-stochastic-processes-driven-by-correlated-noise/</guid>
      <description>Complex systems are difficult to understand. We need good tools to study the interactions that define such systems. In this blog post, we describe how the framework in Mogensen and Hansen (2022) provides such a tool. This summary of the paper is meant to be accessible for readers with some background in statistics or other quantitative sciences. We couldn’t help but include some more specific comments intended for those readers that are familiar with graphical models in statistics.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
