<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Economic Statistics on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/economic-statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Economic Statistics on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/economic-statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Macroeconomic Determinants of Migration. A Comparative Analysis For Old vs New European Member States</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/18/macroeconomic-determinants-of-migration-a-comparative-analysis-for-old-vs-new-european-member-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/18/macroeconomic-determinants-of-migration-a-comparative-analysis-for-old-vs-new-european-member-states/</guid>
      <description>Introduction&#xA;Migration is a multifaceted phenomenon including macro-, meso-, and&#xD;micro-triggers that, when combined, decide an individual’s final&#xD;decision to migrate. Apart from being an essential component of&#xD;population change, migration is also an important component of&#xD;population estimates and labor market force estimations. Jennissen&#xD;(2004) argues that the presence of migrant populations has a favorable&#xD;impact on natural population growth since migrants’ age characteristics&#xD;and fertility rates are often greater than those of the indigenous&#xD;population.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online cash register data in the measurement of retail trade turnover</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/03/abel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/03/abel/</guid>
      <description>The Hungarian Central Statistical Office uses online cash register data for the measurement of retail trade and food services. The data source allows the statistical office to considerably cut administrative burden of data providers without quality loss in retail trade statistics. Online cash register data is widely used in tracking the latest developments in retail trade during the coronavirus pandemic as well.&#xA;Online cash registers (online pénztárgép &amp;ndash; OPG) were introduced in Hungary in 2013.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
