<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Recent advances in extreme value theory</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/04/04/recent-advances-in-extreme-value-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/04/04/recent-advances-in-extreme-value-theory/</guid>
      <description>Recent advances in extreme value theory
Thursday, April 20th, 6:00 PT / 9:00 ET / 15:00 CET
Extreme value theory is concerned with the accurate statistical assessment of the risk of rare events. Such extreme events have small occurrence probabilities but often entail large economic and ecological costs in addition to their potential for severe impacts on human health. There is active research to model and infer complex extremal dependence structures in multivariate data, with connections to high-dimensional statistics, machine learning and other fields.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Log-modulated rough stochastic volatility models</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/14/log-modulated-rough-stochastic-volatility-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/14/log-modulated-rough-stochastic-volatility-models/</guid>
      <description>Rough VolatilityNew insights about the regularity of the instantaneous variance obtainedfrom realized variance data (see Gatheral, Jaisson, and Rosenbaum (2018), Bennedsen, Lunde, and Pakkanen (2021, to appear) and Fukasawa, Takabatake, and Westphal (2019)), have inspiredthe development of so-called rough stochastic volatility modelsin the financial literature. In simple terms, such a model can bedescribed by the following SDE \[\begin{equation}\label{eq:stoch-vol}dS_t = S_t \sqrt{v_t}dB_t,\end{equation}\] where the logarithm of the instantaneous variance process\(v\) behaves similarly to a fractional Brownian motion (fBm) with Hurstindex \(0 &amp;lt; H &amp;lt; 1/2\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Procrustes Analysis for High-Dimensional Data</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/02/procrustes-analysis-for-high-dimensional-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/02/procrustes-analysis-for-high-dimensional-data/</guid>
      <description>OverviewThe Procrustes problem aims to match matrices using similarity transformations (i.e., rotation, reflection, translation, and scaling transformations) to minimize their Frobenius distance. It allows the comparison of matrices with dimensions defined in an arbitrary coordinate system. This method raised the interest of applied researchers, highlighting its potentiality through many applications in several fields, such as ecology, biology, analytical chemometrics, and psychometrics.
The interest of a large audience from applied fields stimulates, in parallel, the growth of a vast body of literature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribution generalization and causal inference</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/02/28/distribution-generalization-in-causal-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/02/28/distribution-generalization-in-causal-inference/</guid>
      <description>Distribution generalization and causal inference
Monday, March 20th, 2023, 7:00 PT / 10:00 ET / 15:00 CET
1st joint webinar of the IMS New Researchers Group, Young Data Science Researcher Seminar Zürich and the YoungStatS Project.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Monday, March 20th, 2023, 7:00 PT / 10:00 ET / 15:00 CETOnline, via Zoom. The registration form is availablehere.Speakers:
Zijian Guo, Rutgers University: “Statistical Inference for Maximin Effects: Identifying Stable Associations across Multiple Studies”Abstract: Integrative analysis of data from multiple sources is critical to making generalizable discoveries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Statistics in Non-Sparse Networks</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/02/26/asymptotic-statistics-in-non-sparse-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/02/26/asymptotic-statistics-in-non-sparse-networks/</guid>
      <description>Exchangeable arrays have been studied since the late 70’s (Aldous (1983),Kallenberg (2005)). Eagleson and Weber (1978) and Silverman (1976) established Strong Law of LargeNumbers and Central Limit Theorems for such arrays. Because non-sparsenetworks and multiway clustering are related to exchangeable arrays,they have received recent attention in statistics and econometrics(Davezies, D’Haultfœuille, and Guyonvarch (2018), Davezies, D’Haultfœuille, and Guyonvarch (2021), Menzel (2018)). We focus below on non-sparse networksand present uniformity results at the basis of the asymptotic normalityof many nonlinear estimators.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fitting robust non-Gaussian models in Stan and R-INLA</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/01/19/fitting-robust-non-gaussian-models-in-stan-and-r-inla/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/01/19/fitting-robust-non-gaussian-models-in-stan-and-r-inla/</guid>
      <description>OverviewTraditionally the excitation noise of spatial and temporal models is Gaussian. Take, for instance, an AR1 (autoregressive of order 1) process, where the increments \(x_{i+1}-\rho x_i, \ \ |\rho|&amp;lt;1\) are assumed to follow a Gaussian distribution. However, it is easy to find datasets that contain inherently non-Gaussian features, such as sudden jumps or spikes, that adversely affect the inferences and predictions made from Gaussian models. In this post, we introduce a specific class of non-Gaussian models, their advantages over Gaussian models, and their Bayesian implementation in Stan and R-INLA, two well-established platforms for statistical modeling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Merry Christmas and Happy New Year 2023!</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/12/21/merry-christmas-and-happy-new-year-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/12/21/merry-christmas-and-happy-new-year-2023/</guid>
      <description>Dear Followers of the YoungStatS project, Dear All!
It has been an exciting year for our project, including 7 One World YoungStatS webinars and blogposts from leading authors in various areas of statistics, probability and econometrics.
In particular, we wish to thank our supporters: The Federation of European National Statistical Societies (FENStatS), Bernoulli Society for Mathematical Statistics and Probability and the Institute of Mathematical Statistics (IMS).
And we thank You, readers of our postings and participants at our webinars for your support and feedback thus far!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weighted residual empirical processes in semi-parametric copula adjusted for regression</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/12/07/weighted-residual-empirical-processes-in-semi-parametric-copula-adjusted-for-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/12/07/weighted-residual-empirical-processes-in-semi-parametric-copula-adjusted-for-regression/</guid>
      <description>OverviewIn this post we first review the concept of semi-parametric copula andthe accompanying estimation procedure of pseudo-likelihood estimation(PLE). We then generalize the estimation problem to the setting wherethe copula signal is hidden in a semi- or non-parametric regressionmodel. Under this setting we have to base the PLE on the residuals. Theparticular challenge of the diverging score function is handled via thetechnique of the weighted residual empirical processes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Recent Developments in Mixture Cure Model Methodology for Survival Analysis</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/30/some-recent-developments-in-mixture-cure-model-methodology-for-survival-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/30/some-recent-developments-in-mixture-cure-model-methodology-for-survival-analysis/</guid>
      <description>AbstractThe mixture cure model in survival analysis has received large and growing attention in the last few decades. Here we present an overview drawing together early results and some recent new developments, and pointing out areas where further work is needed.
Introduction: the Mixture Cure ModelIn certain clinical trials or observational studies, either prospective or based on historically accumulated data, individuals are or have been followed up for a period of time and their status at some endpoint reported.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graphical modeling of stochastic processes driven by correlated noise</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/27/graphical-modeling-of-stochastic-processes-driven-by-correlated-noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/27/graphical-modeling-of-stochastic-processes-driven-by-correlated-noise/</guid>
      <description>Complex systems are difficult to understand. We need good tools to study the interactions that define such systems. In this blog post, we describe how the framework in Mogensen and Hansen (2022) provides such a tool. This summary of the paper is meant to be accessible for readers with some background in statistics or other quantitative sciences. We couldn’t help but include some more specific comments intended for those readers that are familiar with graphical models in statistics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
