<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Linear-cost unbiased estimator for large crossed random effect models via couplings</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/09/27/linear-cost-unbiased-estimator-for-large-crossed-random-effect-models-via-couplings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/09/27/linear-cost-unbiased-estimator-for-large-crossed-random-effect-models-via-couplings/</guid>
      <description>In the following we show how it is possible to obtain parallelizable, unbiased and computationally cheap estimates of Crossed random effects models with a linear cost in the number of datapoints (and paramaters) exploiting couplings.
Crossed random effects models (CREM)CREM model a continuous response variables \(Y\) as depending on the sum of unknown effects of \(K\) categorical predictors. Think of the \(Y_n\) as the ratings given to university courses, along with some factors potentially impacting such a score, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Fairness</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/09/19/algorithmic-fairness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/09/19/algorithmic-fairness/</guid>
      <description>Algorithmic Fairness
Tuesday, October 3rd, 2023, 7:30 PT / 10:30 ET / 16:30 CET
2nd joint webinar of the IMS New Researchers Group, Young Data Science Researcher Seminar Zürich and the YoungStatS Project.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Tuesday, October 3rd, 2023, 7:30 PT / 10:30 ET / 15:30 CETOnline, via Zoom. The registration form is availablehere.Speakers:
Linjun Zhang, Rutgers University: “Fair conformal prediction”Abstract: Multi-calibration is a powerful and evolving concept originating in the field of algorithmic fairness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Illustration of Graphical Gaussian Process models to analyze highly multivariate spatial data</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/07/07/illustration-of-graphical-gaussian-process-models-to-analyze-highly-multivariate-spatial-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/07/07/illustration-of-graphical-gaussian-process-models-to-analyze-highly-multivariate-spatial-data/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionAbundant multivariate spatial data from the natural and environmental sciences demands research on the joint distribution of multiple spatially dependent variables (Wackernagel (2013), Cressie and Wikle (2011), Banerjee and Gelfand (2014)). Here, our goal is to estimate associations over spatial locations for each variable and those among the variables.
In this document, we will present an example of a simulated multivariate spatial data and how we can use Graphical Gaussian processes (GGP) (Dey and Banerjee (2021)) to model the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The scaling limit of Baxter permutations</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/07/02/the-scaling-limit-of-baxter-permutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/07/02/the-scaling-limit-of-baxter-permutations/</guid>
      <description>Meanders, monotone meanders, and Baxter permutationsVersions of the following question can be traced back at least to the work of Henri Poincaré (Poincaré (1912)):
In how many ways a simple loop in the plane can cross a line a specified number of times?
Despite many efforts, this question remains open after more than a century.Let us start by mathematically formalizing the latter question.
Definition 1.1. A meander of size \(n\in\mathbb{N}\) is a simple loop \(\ell\) (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian nonparametric modeling of conditional multidimensional dependence structures</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/05/19/bayesian-nonparametric-modeling-of-conditional-multidimensional-dependence-structures/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/05/19/bayesian-nonparametric-modeling-of-conditional-multidimensional-dependence-structures/</guid>
      <description>OverviewIn many real data applications we are often required to model jointly \(d\geq 3\) continuous random variables, denoted as \(Y_1,\dots,Y_d\) . The multivariate distribution, which allows us to describe the joint behaviour of those variables, can be denoted as \(F(Y_1,\dots,Y_d)=P(Y_1\le y_1,\dots,Y_d,\le y_d)\) . However, complex relations between data, particularly asymmetric and tail dependent associations, are often difficult to be modelled. The copula approach allows us to express the multivariate distribution of a set of variables by separating the marginals from the dependence structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chaotic mixing and the statistical properties of scalar turbulence</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/04/10/chaotic-mixing-and-the-statistical-properties-of-scalar-turbulence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/04/10/chaotic-mixing-and-the-statistical-properties-of-scalar-turbulence/</guid>
      <description>Passive scalar turbulence is the study of how a scalar quantity, such astemperature or salinity, is transported by an incompressible fluid. Thisprocess is modeled by the advection diffusion equation\[\begin{equation}\partial_tg_t + u_t\cdot\nabla g_t - \kappa \Delta g_t = s_t,\label{eqAD}\tag{AD}\end{equation}\] where \(g_t\) is the scalar quantity, \(u_t\) is anincompressible velocity field, \(\kappa&amp;gt;0\) is the diffusivity parameterand \(s_t\) is a replenishing source. As \(g_t\) evolves, it often settlesinto a statistical steady state and complex self-similar structuresarise due to repeated stretching and folding by the velocity field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent advances in extreme value theory</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/04/04/recent-advances-in-extreme-value-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/04/04/recent-advances-in-extreme-value-theory/</guid>
      <description>Recent advances in extreme value theory
Thursday, April 20th, 6:00 PT / 9:00 ET / 15:00 CET
Extreme value theory is concerned with the accurate statistical assessment of the risk of rare events. Such extreme events have small occurrence probabilities but often entail large economic and ecological costs in addition to their potential for severe impacts on human health. There is active research to model and infer complex extremal dependence structures in multivariate data, with connections to high-dimensional statistics, machine learning and other fields.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Log-modulated rough stochastic volatility models</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/14/log-modulated-rough-stochastic-volatility-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/14/log-modulated-rough-stochastic-volatility-models/</guid>
      <description>Rough VolatilityNew insights about the regularity of the instantaneous variance obtainedfrom realized variance data (see Gatheral, Jaisson, and Rosenbaum (2018), Bennedsen, Lunde, and Pakkanen (2021, to appear) and Fukasawa, Takabatake, and Westphal (2019)), have inspiredthe development of so-called rough stochastic volatility modelsin the financial literature. In simple terms, such a model can bedescribed by the following SDE \[\begin{equation}\label{eq:stoch-vol}dS_t = S_t \sqrt{v_t}dB_t,\end{equation}\] where the logarithm of the instantaneous variance process\(v\) behaves similarly to a fractional Brownian motion (fBm) with Hurstindex \(0 &amp;lt; H &amp;lt; 1/2\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Procrustes Analysis for High-Dimensional Data</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/02/procrustes-analysis-for-high-dimensional-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/03/02/procrustes-analysis-for-high-dimensional-data/</guid>
      <description>OverviewThe Procrustes problem aims to match matrices using similarity transformations (i.e., rotation, reflection, translation, and scaling transformations) to minimize their Frobenius distance. It allows the comparison of matrices with dimensions defined in an arbitrary coordinate system. This method raised the interest of applied researchers, highlighting its potentiality through many applications in several fields, such as ecology, biology, analytical chemometrics, and psychometrics.
The interest of a large audience from applied fields stimulates, in parallel, the growth of a vast body of literature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribution generalization and causal inference</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/02/28/distribution-generalization-in-causal-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/02/28/distribution-generalization-in-causal-inference/</guid>
      <description>Distribution generalization and causal inference
Monday, March 20th, 2023, 7:00 PT / 10:00 ET / 15:00 CET
1st joint webinar of the IMS New Researchers Group, Young Data Science Researcher Seminar Zürich and the YoungStatS Project.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Monday, March 20th, 2023, 7:00 PT / 10:00 ET / 15:00 CETOnline, via Zoom. The registration form is availablehere.Speakers:
Zijian Guo, Rutgers University: “Statistical Inference for Maximin Effects: Identifying Stable Associations across Multiple Studies”Abstract: Integrative analysis of data from multiple sources is critical to making generalizable discoveries.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
