<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Macroeconomic Determinants of Migration. A Comparative Analysis For Old vs New European Member States</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/18/macroeconomic-determinants-of-migration-a-comparative-analysis-for-old-vs-new-european-member-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/18/macroeconomic-determinants-of-migration-a-comparative-analysis-for-old-vs-new-european-member-states/</guid>
      <description>Introduction
Migration is a multifaceted phenomenon including macro-, meso-, andmicro-triggers that, when combined, decide an individual’s finaldecision to migrate. Apart from being an essential component ofpopulation change, migration is also an important component ofpopulation estimates and labor market force estimations. Jennissen(2004) argues that the presence of migrant populations has a favorableimpact on natural population growth since migrants’ age characteristicsand fertility rates are often greater than those of the indigenouspopulation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minimax Estimation and Identity Testing of Markov Chains</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/18/minimax-estimation-and-identity-testing-of-markov-chains/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/09/18/minimax-estimation-and-identity-testing-of-markov-chains/</guid>
      <description>We briefly review the two classical problems of distribution estimationand identity testing (in the context of property testing), then proposeto extend them to a Markovian setting. We will see that the samplecomplexity depends not only on the number of states, but also on thestationary and mixing properties of the chains.
The distribution settingEstimation/Learning. A fundamental problem in statistics is toestimate a probability distribution from independent samples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regularization by Noise for Stochastic Differential and Stochastic Partial Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/06/03/regularization-by-noise-for-stochastic-differential-and-stochastic-partial-differential-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/06/03/regularization-by-noise-for-stochastic-differential-and-stochastic-partial-differential-equations/</guid>
      <description>Regularization by Noise for Stochastic Differential and Stochastic Partial Differential Equations
The regularizing effects of noisy perturbations of differential equations is a central subject of stochastic analysis. Recent breakthroughs initiated a new wave of interest, particularly concerning non-Markovian, infinite dimensional, and rough-stochastic / Young-stochastic hybrid systems.
On the webinar, selected younger scholars will present their recent works on the topic.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Wednesday, September 21st, 7:00 PT / 10:00 EST / 16:00 CET.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Theory and Methods for Inference in Multi-armed Bandit Problems</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/04/19/theory-and-methods-for-inference-in-multi-armed-bandit-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/04/19/theory-and-methods-for-inference-in-multi-armed-bandit-problems/</guid>
      <description>Theory and Methods for Inference in Multi-armed Bandit Problems
Multi-armed bandit (MAB) algorithms have been argued for decades as useful to conduct adaptively-randomized experiments. By skewing the allocation of the arms towards the more efficient or informative ones, they have the potential to enhance participants’ welfare, while resulting in a more flexible, efficient, and ethical alternative compared to traditional fixed studies. However, such allocation strategies complicate the problem of statistical inference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selection of Priors in Bayesian Structural Equation Modeling</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/14/selection-of-priors-in-bayesian-structural-equation-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/14/selection-of-priors-in-bayesian-structural-equation-modeling/</guid>
      <description>Selection of Priors in Bayesian Structural Equation Modelling
Structural equation modeling (SEM) is an important framework within the social sciences that encompasses a wide variety of statistical models. Traditionally, estimation of SEMs has relied on maximum likelihood. Unfortunately, there also exist a variety of situations in which maximum likelihood performs subpar. This led researchers to turn to alternative estimation methods, in particular, Bayesian estimation of SEMs or BSEM. However, it is currently unclear how to specify the prior distribution in order to attain the advantages of Bayesian approaches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in Approximate Bayesian Inference</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/08/recent-advances-in-approximate-bayesian-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/08/recent-advances-in-approximate-bayesian-inference/</guid>
      <description>Recent Advances in Approximate Bayesian Inference
In approximate Bayesian computation, likelihood function is intractable and needs to be itself estimated using forward simulations of the statistical model (Beaumont et al., 2002; Marin et al., 2012; Sisson et al., 2019; Martin et al., 2020). Recent years have seen numerous advances in approximate inference methods, which have enabled Bayesian inference in increasingly challenging scenarios involving complex probabilistic models and large datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advancements in Applied Instrumental Variable Methods</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/07/recent-advancements-in-applied-instrumental-variable-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/07/recent-advancements-in-applied-instrumental-variable-methods/</guid>
      <description>Recent Advancements in Applied Instrumental Variable Methods
Instrumental variables (IV) is one of most important and widespread research designs in economics and statistics, as it can identify causal effects in the presence of unobserved confounding. Over the past 30 years the science of IV has advanced considerably, in part through the contributions of Nobel Laureates Joshua Angrist, Guido Imbens, and James Heckman. Recent years have brought significant advances in how IV is applied, in shift-share designs, with judge or examiner instruments, and in settings with rich or complex controls.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring dependence in the Wasserstein distance for Bayesian nonparametric models</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/17/measuring-dependence-in-the-wasserstein-distance-for-bayesian-nonparametric-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/17/measuring-dependence-in-the-wasserstein-distance-for-bayesian-nonparametric-models/</guid>
      <description>OverviewBayesian nonparametric (BNP) models are a prominent tool for performing flexible inference with a natural quantification of uncertainty. Traditionallly, flexible inference within a homogeneous sample is performed with exchangeable models of the type \(X_1,\dots, X_n|\tilde \mu \sim T(\tilde \mu)\), where \(\tilde \mu\) is a random measure and \(T\) is a suitable transformation. Notable examples for \(T\) include normalization for random probabilities (Regazzini et al., 2003), kernel mixtures for densities (Lo, 1984) and for hazards (Dykstra and Laud, 1981; James, 2005), exponential transformations for survival functions (Doksum, 1974) and cumulative transformations for cumulative hazards (Hjort, 1990).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Universal estimation with Maximum Mean Discrepancy (MMD)</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/13/universal-estimation-with-maximum-mean-discrepancy-mmd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/13/universal-estimation-with-maximum-mean-discrepancy-mmd/</guid>
      <description>This is an updated version of a blog post on RIKEN AIP Approximate Bayesian Inference team webpage: https://team-approx-bayes.github.io/blog/mmd/
INTRODUCTIONA very old and yet very exciting problem in statistics is the definition of a universal estimator \(\hat{\theta}\). An estimation procedure that would work all the time. Close your eyes, push the button, it works, for any model, in any context.
Formally speaking, we want that for some metric \(d\) on probability distributions, for any statistical model \((P_\theta,\theta\in\Theta)\), given \(X_1,\dots,X_n\) drawn i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reconciling the Gaussian and Whittle Likelihood with an application to estimation in the frequency domain</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/06/reconciling-the-gaussian-and-whittle-likelihood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/06/reconciling-the-gaussian-and-whittle-likelihood/</guid>
      <description>OverviewSuppose \(\{X_t: t\in \mathbb{Z}\}\) is a second order stationary time series where \(c(r) = \text{cov}(X_{t+r},X_t)\) and \(f(\omega) = \sum_{r\in\mathbb{Z}}c(r)e^{ir\omega}\) are the corresponding autocovariance and spectral density function, respectively. For notational convenience, we assume the time series is centered, that is \(\textrm{E}(X_t)=0\).Our aim is to fit a parametric second-order stationary model (specified by \(\{c_{f_\theta}(r)\}\) or \(f_\theta(\omega)\)) to the observed time series \(\underline{X}_n = (X_1, ..., X_n)^\top\).There are two classical estimation methods based on the quasi-likelihood criteria.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
