<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>copula-models on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/copula-models/</link>
    <description>Recent content in copula-models on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/copula-models/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian nonparametric modeling of conditional multidimensional dependence structures</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/05/19/bayesian-nonparametric-modeling-of-conditional-multidimensional-dependence-structures/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2023/05/19/bayesian-nonparametric-modeling-of-conditional-multidimensional-dependence-structures/</guid>
      <description>OverviewIn many real data applications we are often required to model jointly \(d\geq 3\) continuous random variables, denoted as \(Y_1,\dots,Y_d\) . The multivariate distribution, which allows us to describe the joint behaviour of those variables, can be denoted as \(F(Y_1,\dots,Y_d)=P(Y_1\le y_1,\dots,Y_d,\le y_d)\) . However, complex relations between data, particularly asymmetric and tail dependent associations, are often difficult to be modelled. The copula approach allows us to express the multivariate distribution of a set of variables by separating the marginals from the dependence structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weighted residual empirical processes in semi-parametric copula adjusted for regression</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/12/07/weighted-residual-empirical-processes-in-semi-parametric-copula-adjusted-for-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/12/07/weighted-residual-empirical-processes-in-semi-parametric-copula-adjusted-for-regression/</guid>
      <description>OverviewIn this post we first review the concept of semi-parametric copula andthe accompanying estimation procedure of pseudo-likelihood estimation(PLE). We then generalize the estimation problem to the setting wherethe copula signal is hidden in a semi- or non-parametric regressionmodel. Under this setting we have to base the PLE on the residuals. Theparticular challenge of the diverging score function is handled via thetechnique of the weighted residual empirical processes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
