<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Functional-Data-Analysis on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/functional-data-analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Functional-Data-Analysis on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/functional-data-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Nonparametric inference based on statistical depth</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/03/nonparametric-inference-based-on-statistical-depth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/10/03/nonparametric-inference-based-on-statistical-depth/</guid>
      <description>Nonparametric inference based on statistical depth
The notion of center of an object, be it a set of observations, a physical object or a random variable, is difficult to define. This motivated the development of general ways to measure centrality via depth functions. Such mappings allow for comparing relative centrality of two locations and, consequently, providing a center-outward ordering. Many such mappings have been introduced in the literature in recent decades and this is subject to intense research in, among other, nonparametric statistics and functional data analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in Functional Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/29/fda-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/29/fda-webinar/</guid>
      <description>The fourth &amp;ldquo;One World webinar&amp;rdquo; organized by YoungStatS will take place on June 30th, 2021. The topic of this webinar is on Functional Data Analysis. Selected young European researchers active in this area of research will present their contributions on spherical functional autoregressions, additive models, and clustering methods for functional data, with the focus on both theoretical developments and applications.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Wednesday, June 30th, 16:30 CEST
Online, via Zoom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Regression Control Chart: a New Framework for Profile Monitoring
</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/04/functional-regression-control-chart/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/12/04/functional-regression-control-chart/</guid>
      <description>Introduction New statistical process control (SPC) methods have to be developed in order to handle more and more complex data, which are available because of the advent of new data acquisition technologies. In particular, in many practical situations the quality characteristic of a process can be modelled as a function defined on a compact domain, data of such kind are the foundation of a rapidly expanding area of statistics referred to as functional data analysis (FDA).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
