<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Maximum-Likelihood on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/maximum-likelihood/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Maximum-Likelihood on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/maximum-likelihood/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reconciling the Gaussian and Whittle Likelihood with an application to estimation in the frequency domain</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/06/reconciling-the-gaussian-and-whittle-likelihood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/01/06/reconciling-the-gaussian-and-whittle-likelihood/</guid>
      <description>Overview&#xD;Suppose \(\{X_t: t\in \mathbb{Z}\}\) is a second order stationary time series where \(c(r) = \text{cov}(X_{t+r},X_t)\) and \(f(\omega) = \sum_{r\in\mathbb{Z}}c(r)e^{ir\omega}\) are the corresponding autocovariance and spectral density function, respectively. For notational convenience, we assume the time series is centered, that is \(\textrm{E}(X_t)=0\).&#xD;Our aim is to fit a parametric second-order stationary model (specified by \(\{c_{f_\theta}(r)\}\) or \(f_\theta(\omega)\)) to the observed time series \(\underline{X}_n = (X_1, ..., X_n)^\top\).&#xD;There are two classical estimation methods based on the quasi-likelihood criteria.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel Algebraic Approaches to Maximum Likelihood Estimation</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/10/04/novel-algebraic-approaches-to-maximum-likelihood-estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/10/04/novel-algebraic-approaches-to-maximum-likelihood-estimation/</guid>
      <description>Novel Algebraic Approaches to Maximum Likelihood Estimation&#xA;The seventh “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place&#xD;on November 17th, 2021. Maximum likelihood estimation (MLE) is a tool in&#xD;data analysis to estimate a probability distribution or density in a&#xD;statistical model for given data. In recent decades, algebraic and&#xD;combinatorial tools have proved useful for computing MLEs and&#xD;understanding the geometry of the MLE problem which in recent years led&#xD;to new and interesting results in combinatorics and algebraic geometry.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher Order Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/03/10/higher-order-targeted-maximum-likelihood-estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/03/10/higher-order-targeted-maximum-likelihood-estimation/</guid>
      <description>Summary&#xA;We propose a higher order targeted maximum likelihood estimation (TMLE) that only relies on a sequentially and recursively defined set of data-adaptive fluctuations. Without the need to assume the often too stringent higher order pathwise differentiability, the method is practical for implementation and has the potential to be fully computerized.&#xA;Background&#xD;Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation (TMLE)&#xD;It has been particularly of interest for semiparametric theories and real world practices to make efficient and substitution-based estimation for target quantities that are functions of data distribution.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
