<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>webinars on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/webinars/</link>
    <description>Recent content in webinars on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/webinars/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Concentration Inequalities in Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>The fifth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place on September 15th, 2021. Selected young European researchers active in the areas of probability and machine learning will present their recent contributions. The webinar is joint cooperation between the Young Researchers Committee of the Bernoulli Society and the YoungStatS project.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Wednesday, September 15th, 17:00 CESTOnline, via Zoom. The registration form is available here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in Functional Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/29/fda-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/29/fda-webinar/</guid>
      <description>The fourth &amp;ldquo;One World webinar&amp;rdquo; organized by YoungStatS will take place on June 30th, 2021. The topic of this webinar is on Functional Data Analysis. Selected young European researchers active in this area of research will present their contributions on spherical functional autoregressions, additive models, and clustering methods for functional data, with the focus on both theoretical developments and applications.
When &amp;amp; Where:
  Wednesday, June 30th, 16:30 CEST</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Composite-Based Structural Equation Modeling: Developments and Perspectives</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/28/csem-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/28/csem-webinar/</guid>
      <description>The third &amp;ldquo;One World webinar&amp;rdquo; organized by YoungStatS will take place on May 19th, 2021. The focus of this webinar will be on composite-based structural equation modeling, particularly on partial least squares path modeling (Wold, 1982; Lohmöller, 1989) and approaches to assess composite models. The webinar will present some of the most interesting and recent theoretical developments and applications from younger scholars active in this area of research.
When &amp;amp; Where:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developments in Bayesian Nonparametrics (updated with slides)</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/06/bnp-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/06/bnp-webinar/</guid>
      <description>The second &amp;ldquo;One World webinar&amp;rdquo; organized by YoungStatS will take place on April 21st. The focus of this webinar will be on illustrating modern advances in Bayesian Nonparametrics data analysis, discussing challenging theoretical problems and stimulating case-studies within this active area of research.
When &amp;amp; Where:
 Wednesday, April 21st, 16:30 CEST Online, via Zoom. The registration form is available here. Further details and the Zoom link will be sent to the registered addresses only.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in COVID-19 modelling</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/02/04/covid-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/02/04/covid-webinar/</guid>
      <description>YoungStatS project of Young Statisticians Europe, FENStatS, proudly announces our first One World YoungStatS webinar. With four young scholars, we will discuss Recent Advances in the Modelling of COVID-19, presenting novel statistical models, interesting advancements and applications of mechanistic models, as well as their combinations.
When: Wednesday, February 10th, 16:00 (Central European Time).
Speakers:
 Cécile Tran Kiem (Institute Pasteur, Paris, France) Pierfrancesco Alaimo Di Loro and Marco Mingione (StatGroup-19, Italy) Kevin Kunzmann (University of Cambridge, United Kingdom)  Discussant:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One World YoungStatS</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/09/10/webinars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2020/09/10/webinars/</guid>
      <description>One World YoungStatS webinar
We are delighted to announce the creation of the One World YoungStatS Webinar series! Our goal in creating this seminar series is to provide a platform for our community to continue interacting and growing in spite of the current health crisis and ever since. The YoungStatS webinar series will accompany the YoungStatS blog and provide insight into best and most recent work done in all areas of statistics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
