<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>webinars on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/webinars/</link>
    <description>Recent content in webinars on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/webinars/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Regularization by Noise for Stochastic Differential and Stochastic Partial Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/06/03/regularization-by-noise-for-stochastic-differential-and-stochastic-partial-differential-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/06/03/regularization-by-noise-for-stochastic-differential-and-stochastic-partial-differential-equations/</guid>
      <description>Regularization by Noise for Stochastic Differential and Stochastic Partial Differential Equations
The regularizing effects of noisy perturbations of differential equations is a central subject of stochastic analysis. Recent breakthroughs initiated a new wave of interest, particularly concerning non-Markovian, infinite dimensional, and rough-stochastic / Young-stochastic hybrid systems.
On the webinar, selected younger scholars will present their recent works on the topic.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Wednesday, September 21st, 7:00 PT / 10:00 EST / 16:00 CET.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Theory and Methods for Inference in Multi-armed Bandit Problems</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/04/19/theory-and-methods-for-inference-in-multi-armed-bandit-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/04/19/theory-and-methods-for-inference-in-multi-armed-bandit-problems/</guid>
      <description>Theory and Methods for Inference in Multi-armed Bandit Problems
Multi-armed bandit (MAB) algorithms have been argued for decades as useful to conduct adaptively-randomized experiments. By skewing the allocation of the arms towards the more efficient or informative ones, they have the potential to enhance participants’ welfare, while resulting in a more flexible, efficient, and ethical alternative compared to traditional fixed studies. However, such allocation strategies complicate the problem of statistical inference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selection of Priors in Bayesian Structural Equation Modeling</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/14/selection-of-priors-in-bayesian-structural-equation-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/14/selection-of-priors-in-bayesian-structural-equation-modeling/</guid>
      <description>Selection of Priors in Bayesian Structural Equation Modelling
Structural equation modeling (SEM) is an important framework within the social sciences that encompasses a wide variety of statistical models. Traditionally, estimation of SEMs has relied on maximum likelihood. Unfortunately, there also exist a variety of situations in which maximum likelihood performs subpar. This led researchers to turn to alternative estimation methods, in particular, Bayesian estimation of SEMs or BSEM. However, it is currently unclear how to specify the prior distribution in order to attain the advantages of Bayesian approaches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in Approximate Bayesian Inference</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/08/recent-advances-in-approximate-bayesian-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/08/recent-advances-in-approximate-bayesian-inference/</guid>
      <description>Recent Advances in Approximate Bayesian Inference
In approximate Bayesian computation, likelihood function is intractable and needs to be itself estimated using forward simulations of the statistical model (Beaumont et al., 2002; Marin et al., 2012; Sisson et al., 2019; Martin et al., 2020). Recent years have seen numerous advances in approximate inference methods, which have enabled Bayesian inference in increasingly challenging scenarios involving complex probabilistic models and large datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advancements in Applied Instrumental Variable Methods</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/07/recent-advancements-in-applied-instrumental-variable-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/07/recent-advancements-in-applied-instrumental-variable-methods/</guid>
      <description>Recent Advancements in Applied Instrumental Variable Methods
Instrumental variables (IV) is one of most important and widespread research designs in economics and statistics, as it can identify causal effects in the presence of unobserved confounding. Over the past 30 years the science of IV has advanced considerably, in part through the contributions of Nobel Laureates Joshua Angrist, Guido Imbens, and James Heckman. Recent years have brought significant advances in how IV is applied, in shift-share designs, with judge or examiner instruments, and in settings with rich or complex controls.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inclusion Process and Sticky Brownian Motions</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/24/inclusion-process-and-sticky-brownian-motions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/24/inclusion-process-and-sticky-brownian-motions/</guid>
      <description>Inclusion Process and Sticky Brownian Motions
The ninth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place onFebruary 9th, 2022. Inclusion process (IP) is a stochastic lattice gaswhere particles perform random walks subjected to mutual attraction. Forthe inclusion process in the condensation regime one can extract thatthe scaling limit of two particles is a pair of sticky Brownian motionswhich lead to interesting recent research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel Algebraic Approaches to Maximum Likelihood Estimation</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/10/04/novel-algebraic-approaches-to-maximum-likelihood-estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/10/04/novel-algebraic-approaches-to-maximum-likelihood-estimation/</guid>
      <description>Novel Algebraic Approaches to Maximum Likelihood Estimation
The seventh “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take placeon November 17th, 2021. Maximum likelihood estimation (MLE) is a tool indata analysis to estimate a probability distribution or density in astatistical model for given data. In recent decades, algebraic andcombinatorial tools have proved useful for computing MLEs andunderstanding the geometry of the MLE problem which in recent years ledto new and interesting results in combinatorics and algebraic geometry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advancements in Symbolic Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advancements-in-symbolic-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advancements-in-symbolic-data-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Advancements in Symbolic Data Analysis
The sixth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place onNovember 8th, 2021. With the development of digital systems, very largedatasets have become routine. However, standard statistical approachesdo not have the power or flexibility to analyse these efficiently, andextract the required knowledge. Symbolic Data Analysis provides aframework allowing for the representation of data with intrinsicvariability, where the observed “values” are not just single real valuesor categories, but finite sets, intervals or distributions over a givendomain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advances in Difference-in-Differences in Econometrics</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advances-in-difference-in-differences-in-econometrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advances-in-difference-in-differences-in-econometrics/</guid>
      <description>Advances in Difference-in-Differences in Econometrics
The eighth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take placeon December 15th, 2021. The difference-in-differences design is aquasi-experimental identification strategy for estimating causal effectswhich has become the single most popular research design in thequantitative social sciences, and as such, it merits careful study byresearchers everywhere. It is also a flourishing field of presentresearch in econometrics. Selected younger researchers active in thearea will present their recent contributions on this topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Concentration Inequalities in Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>The fifth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place on September 15th, 2021. Selected young European researchers active in the areas of probability and machine learning will present their recent contributions. The webinar is joint cooperation between the Young Researchers Committee of the Bernoulli Society and the YoungStatS project.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Wednesday, September 15th, 17:00 CESTOnline, via Zoom. The registration form is available here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
