<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>webinars on YoungStatS</title>
    <link>https://youngstats.github.io/categories/webinars/</link>
    <description>Recent content in webinars on YoungStatS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://youngstats.github.io/categories/webinars/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in Approximate Bayesian Inference</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/08/recent-advances-in-approximate-bayesian-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/08/recent-advances-in-approximate-bayesian-inference/</guid>
      <description>Recent Advances in Approximate Bayesian Inference
In approximate Bayesian computation, likelihood function is intractable and needs to be itself estimated using forward simulations of the statistical model (Beaumont et al., 2002; Marin et al., 2012; Sisson et al., 2019; Martin et al., 2020). Recent years have seen numerous advances in approximate inference methods, which have enabled Bayesian inference in increasingly challenging scenarios involving complex probabilistic models and large datasets.
On the webinar, selected young statisticians will present their recent works on the topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advancements in Applied Instrumental Variable Methods</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/07/recent-advancements-in-applied-instrumental-variable-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2022/02/07/recent-advancements-in-applied-instrumental-variable-methods/</guid>
      <description>Recent Advancements in Applied Instrumental Variable Methods
Instrumental variables (IV) is one of most important and widespread research designs in economics and statistics, as it can identify causal effects in the presence of unobserved confounding. Over the past 30 years the science of IV has advanced considerably, in part through the contributions of Nobel Laureates Joshua Angrist, Guido Imbens, and James Heckman. Recent years have brought significant advances in how IV is applied, in shift-share designs, with judge or examiner instruments, and in settings with rich or complex controls.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inclusion Process and Sticky Brownian Motions</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/24/inclusion-process-and-sticky-brownian-motions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/12/24/inclusion-process-and-sticky-brownian-motions/</guid>
      <description>Inclusion Process and Sticky Brownian Motions
The ninth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place on February 9th, 2022. Inclusion process (IP) is a stochastic lattice gas where particles perform random walks subjected to mutual attraction. For the inclusion process in the condensation regime one can extract that the scaling limit of two particles is a pair of sticky Brownian motions which lead to interesting recent research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel Algebraic Approaches to Maximum Likelihood Estimation</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/10/04/novel-algebraic-approaches-to-maximum-likelihood-estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/10/04/novel-algebraic-approaches-to-maximum-likelihood-estimation/</guid>
      <description>Novel Algebraic Approaches to Maximum Likelihood Estimation
The seventh “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take placeon November 17th, 2021. Maximum likelihood estimation (MLE) is a tool indata analysis to estimate a probability distribution or density in astatistical model for given data. In recent decades, algebraic andcombinatorial tools have proved useful for computing MLEs andunderstanding the geometry of the MLE problem which in recent years ledto new and interesting results in combinatorics and algebraic geometry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advancements in Symbolic Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advancements-in-symbolic-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advancements-in-symbolic-data-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Advancements in Symbolic Data Analysis
The sixth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place onNovember 8th, 2021. With the development of digital systems, very largedatasets have become routine. However, standard statistical approachesdo not have the power or flexibility to analyse these efficiently, andextract the required knowledge. Symbolic Data Analysis provides aframework allowing for the representation of data with intrinsicvariability, where the observed “values” are not just single real valuesor categories, but finite sets, intervals or distributions over a givendomain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advances in Difference-in-Differences in Econometrics</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advances-in-difference-in-differences-in-econometrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/09/30/advances-in-difference-in-differences-in-econometrics/</guid>
      <description>Advances in Difference-in-Differences in Econometrics
The eighth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take placeon December 15th, 2021. The difference-in-differences design is aquasi-experimental identification strategy for estimating causal effectswhich has become the single most popular research design in thequantitative social sciences, and as such, it merits careful study byresearchers everywhere. It is also a flourishing field of presentresearch in econometrics. Selected younger researchers active in thearea will present their recent contributions on this topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Concentration Inequalities in Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/06/30/concentration-inequalities-in-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>The fifth “One World webinar” organized by YoungStatS will take place on September 15th, 2021. Selected young European researchers active in the areas of probability and machine learning will present their recent contributions. The webinar is joint cooperation between the Young Researchers Committee of the Bernoulli Society and the YoungStatS project.
When &amp;amp; Where:
Wednesday, September 15th, 17:00 CESTOnline, via Zoom. The registration form is available here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in Functional Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/29/fda-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/29/fda-webinar/</guid>
      <description>The fourth &amp;ldquo;One World webinar&amp;rdquo; organized by YoungStatS will take place on June 30th, 2021. The topic of this webinar is on Functional Data Analysis. Selected young European researchers active in this area of research will present their contributions on spherical functional autoregressions, additive models, and clustering methods for functional data, with the focus on both theoretical developments and applications.
When &amp;amp; Where:
  Wednesday, June 30th, 16:30 CEST</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Composite-Based Structural Equation Modeling: Developments and Perspectives</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/28/csem-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/28/csem-webinar/</guid>
      <description>The third &amp;ldquo;One World webinar&amp;rdquo; organized by YoungStatS will take place on May 19th, 2021. The focus of this webinar will be on composite-based structural equation modeling, particularly on partial least squares path modeling (Wold, 1982; Lohmöller, 1989) and approaches to assess composite models. The webinar will present some of the most interesting and recent theoretical developments and applications from younger scholars active in this area of research.
When &amp;amp; Where:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developments in Bayesian Nonparametrics (updated with slides)</title>
      <link>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/06/bnp-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://youngstats.github.io/post/2021/04/06/bnp-webinar/</guid>
      <description>The second &amp;ldquo;One World webinar&amp;rdquo; organized by YoungStatS will take place on April 21st. The focus of this webinar will be on illustrating modern advances in Bayesian Nonparametrics data analysis, discussing challenging theoretical problems and stimulating case-studies within this active area of research.
When &amp;amp; Where:
 Wednesday, April 21st, 16:30 CEST Online, via Zoom. The registration form is available here. Further details and the Zoom link will be sent to the registered addresses only.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
